Okay, so let's talk about the definition
of a project now.
Now, PMI defines the project
as a temporary endeavor
undertaken to create a unique
product, service, or result.
So this is PMI's exact definition of a
project, and it has been for a long,
long time.
The exact definition from
PMI is a temporary endeavor
undertaken to create a
unique product service or result.
and there's three key terms here.
Three key terms are temporary,
unique, and result.
So temporary, unique,
and, you know, you're
creating something, some kind of result.
So let's talk about each of these three
terms.
First one, temporary.
Temporary means it has a beginning and an
end.
You start your project on one day,
you finish it on another day, as opposed
to ongoing operations, where you're doing
the same thing over, and over again,
right?
You're repeating the product, right?
You're repeating the service.
You're doing the same thing over and over
again.
Now, there's a lot of overlap between
projects and ongoing operations.
And every organization, every
industry may have their own
definition of what they call a
project or an ongoing operation.
Here, we're just looking at very,
very high level.
Right.
So just overall, very broadly,
from PMI's perspective, 60,000 foot level.
A project, is temporary.
It has a beginning and an end.
Now, what's a timeline in between?
Irrelevant.
It could be a few days, a few weeks,
a few months, a few years, but you
definitely have a start date and then
there's an end.
So that's one part of the definition of a
project.
It's temporary at the beginning and an
end.
Another part of the definition,
you're producing something unique.
So, project is a temporary
endeavor undertaken
to create a unique
product service or result.
Unique means it's something different to
what we had before.
Unique doesn't necessarily mean it's
something we've never done before.
I mean, that does fall within that
definition, but unique is more,
it's something different to what we had
before.
So, for example, you're upgrading your
computer system, right?
You're upgrading from version 1.0 to
version 2.0.
Well, version 2.0, well,
version 2.0, has some features
that make it unique
compared to the prior version.
So unique is just it's something
different.
So you could be doing the same project but
for a different customer.
It's a unique customer.
Or you're doing the same project but in a
different location.
It's a unique location.
So unique is just it's
something different,
something different to what we had before.
And then the other part of the definition
is a result.
There's some kind of result.
at the end of it.
Right?
It could be a product, a physical product,
or a service.
It could be a change to a process,
a new process, right?
Or a different process.
Or certainly it's going to be some
documentation.
The result could be a documentation.
But there's something at the end of it.
So even if it's nothing
more than a decision,
the result could actually be a decision.
You don't have to have a physical product
or a service.
Think, for example, of a feasibility
study.
Sometimes a feasibility study could be an
entire project by itself.
Building a road, you're building a dam,
you're building a power station.
You have to do a feasibility study.
Feasibility study may take several years.
That might be a project all by itself.
But have we actually built anything at the
end of the feasibility study?
No.
All we're doing is making a decision.
We've got tons and tons of documentation.
And we're going to make
a decision at the end of
the feasibility study,
at the end of the project.
So a result then could
be a physical product
or service or it could
be something intangible.
So that is PMI's exact definition then of
a project.
It's a temporary endeavor undertaken to
create a unique product, service or result.
Now, a couple of things I have to consider
here.
One of the major things
is, what's the project to one
team could be an ongoing
operation to another team?
So point of view is very much.
important here as well when we're talking
about projects.
So let's just think of something very,
very simple.
Think of a call center.
Call center is all ongoing operations.
Are you doing the same thing over and over
again?
Call center operator just doing the same
thing over and over
again, taking phone calls.
Now, what if there was supposed to be,
or there's anticipation that there's going
to be a huge increase in the number of
calls, right?
Just say for a couple of months and we
need to bring in some temporary stuff.
So just for those couple of months,
you bring in some temporary staff.
Now, as far as a regular
call center operators
are concerned, there's
increasing number of calls.
To them, it's business as usual,
right?
It's still ongoing operations as far as
they're concerned.
But ask one of the temporary staff to you,
is this a project or an ongoing operation?
Well, from their point of view,
it might be a project.
And why?
Because they hear temporarily,
they have a definite start date, right?
they're only here for, say, two months and
they're going to leave.
They have a definite start date and an end
date.
They're here temporarily.
Plus, this is a unique environment as far
as they're concerned.
We didn't work in this call center before.
They were working some
other call center before, or
they might not have been
working in a call center.
This is a service that they're providing.
So as far as they're
concerned, this is a unique
service compared to what
they were doing before.
So point of view is important.
Right, whose point of view are we looking
at?
Because what is a
project to one team could
be an ongoing operation to another team.
Another kind of like,
basic difference, if you
like, between projects and,
say, ongoing operations.
Adding new functionality, adding new
functionality is generally
considered a project.
Tweaking or modifying
functionality that's already
there would generally be
considered ongoing operations.
Okay.
Now, there's another term, in fact,
there's a couple of other terms that are
very, very important and related to a
project that I want to explain here.
And one of those is this term here,
progressive elaboration.
Now, you've all come across progressive
elaboration.
We use progressive elaborations throughout
our entire life, right?
But basically what progressive elaboration
refers to is the fact that you're Starting
off with something high
level and then drilling down
into the details until
you get the final product.
So when you start off on
a project, you don't know
everything there is to
know about the project.
You have enough information just to get
started.
You have a high level concept.
This is what we want from this project.
Then from that high level
concept, you're going to
come up with the high
level scope of the project.
And then you're going to come down to some
of the more details.
And then you're going to come up with a
high level activity.
and then drill it down into more detail
activities until you get your final
project or rather until you get your final
product right that is progressive
elaboration right you're constantly
constantly drilling down into the details
so you're making updates you're constantly
making updates to your project plans your
budget your timelines and um risk register
issues log and all of the all of the plans
a risk management plan and
the schedule management plan
and the quality management
plan and so and so forth.
You're drilling down into all of the
details, right?
So your project plans are dynamic.
They're constantly, continuously being
updated as more information is gathered.
And we do that every aspect of life,
right?
Use take small baby steps before you can
start running.
I mean, in everything you do, you start
off with something high level and then you
start drilling down to the details,
right, until you get a final product.
Even something as simple as, like, say
doing a PowerPoint presentation, right?
You need to give a presentation,
right?
Say an hour long presentation.
Well, you don't just suddenly
sit down for, you know,
10 minutes and write up
an hour long presentation.
No, you start off with a high level
concept, right, a high level plan.
All right, these are what I'm going to be
talking about.
These are the topics I'm going to be
Yeah, you're going to come up with some
high level, high level slides,
high level slide deck.
Then you're going to start putting in more
and more detail, right?
They're going to move details around.
You're going to tweet.
it until you get to your final product.
Again, that is progressive elaboration.
So your project is constantly
progressively elaborated.
We're constantly making updates as more
information is gathered.
Now a type of progressive elaboration is
something called rolling wave planning.
And rolling wave planning, as I said,
it's a type of progressive elaboration.
It's where you are planning
near-term items in detail
and longer-term items at
a much more higher level.
And this is generally used in iterative,
incremental type methodologies,
agile methodologies, all use rolling wave.
You're planning near-term items in detail,
longer term, at a much more high level.
So, for example, then,
let's say we are in the testing
phase of a project and we
have three iterations of testing.
Why do we have three iterations of
testing?
Well, because we don't know exactly
everything that needs to be tested.
So we are going to plan all the testing
for iteration 1 immediately, initially.
And the reason why we don't know
everything that needs to be tested is
because, as we are testing, there might be
some additional tests, right, that might
be discovered, that might, you know,
these tests might spawn off some
additional tests that we don't know about
yet.
So we're going to plan iteration 1 in a
lot of detail, iteration 2 and 3,
you know, at a much more high level.
These are the milestones we want to hit
for 2 and 3.
once we start getting results from
iteration one then we can start planning
iteration two in detail and so and so
forth so we're not planning the entire
phase all in one go we're planning in
stages we're planning in waves and that's
what rolling wave planning is so in an
agile environment those iterations are
known as Springs so you're planning each
sprint in detail one by one you're not
planning every single sprint in detail
right at the beginning.
You are first going to plan the current
sprint.
As you get to each sprint, you're going to
plan each sprint in detail at that time.
All the other sprints are going to be
planned at a much more high level.
So that is rolling wave planning, which
is a type of progressive elaboration.
And your project is constantly
progressively elaborated.
Okay.